<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="bcp"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-iops-grow-bgp-session-culling-00"
     submissionType="IETF">

    <front>

        <title abbrev="BGP Session Culling">Mitigating Negative Impact of Maintenance through BGP Session Culling</title>

        <author fullname="Will Hargrave" initials="W." surname="Hargrave">
            <organization abbrev="LONAP">LONAP Ltd</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>5 Fleet Place</street>
                    <city>London</city>
                    <code>EC4M 7RD</code>
                    <country>United Kingdom</country>
                </postal>
                <email>will@lonap.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Matt Griswold" initials="M." surname="Griswold">
            <organization abbrev="20C">20C</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1658 Milwaukee Ave # 100-4506</street>
                    <city>Chicago</city>
                    <region>IL</region>
                    <code>60647</code>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </postal>
                <email>grizz@20c.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>


        <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
            <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT Communications</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Theodorus Majofskistraat 100</street>
                    <code>1065 SZ</code>
                    <city>Amsterdam</city>
                    <country>NL</country>
                </postal>
                <email>job@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date />

        <area>Routing</area>
        <workgroup>Global Routing Operations</workgroup>
        <keyword>BGP</keyword>
        <keyword>culling</keyword>
        <keyword>EBGP</keyword>
        <keyword>sessions</keyword>

        <abstract>
            <t>
                This document outlines an approach to mitigate negative impact on networks resulting from maintenance activities.
                It includes guidance for both IP networks and Internet Exchange Points (IXPs).
                The approach is to ensure BGP-4 sessions affected by the maintenance are forcefully torn down before the actual maintenance activities commence.
            </t>
        </abstract>

        <note title="Requirements Language">
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
            </t>
        </note>

    </front>


    <middle>
        <section anchor="Introduction" title="Introduction">
            <t>
                In network topologies where BGP speaking routers are directly attached to each other, or use fault detection mechanisms such as <xref target="RFC5880">BFD</xref>, detecting and acting upon a link down event (for example when someone yanks the physical connector) in a timely fashion is straightforward.
            </t>
            <t>
                However, in topologies where upper layer fast fault detection mechanisms are unavailable and the lower layer topology is hidden from the BGP speakers, operators rely on BGP Hold Timer Expiration (section 6.5 of <xref target="RFC4271" />) to initiate traffic rerouting.
                Common BGP Hold Timer values are anywhere between 90 and 180 seconds, which implies a window of 90 to 180 seconds during which traffic blackholing will occur if the lower layer network is not able to forward traffic.
            </t>
            <t>
                BGP Session Culling is the practise of ensuring BGP sessions are forcefully torn down before maintenance activities on a lower layer network commence, which otherwise would affect the flow of data between the BGP speakers.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="BGP Session Culling">
            <t>
                From the viewpoint of the IP network operator, there are two types of BGP Session Culling:
                <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Voluntary BGP Session Teardown:">The operator initiates the tear down of the potentially affected BGP session by issuing an Administrative Shutdown.</t>
                    <t hangText="Involuntary BGP Session Teardown:">The caretaker of the lower layer network disrupts BGP control-plane traffic in the upper layer, causing the BGP Hold Timers of the affected BGP session to expire, subsequently triggering rerouting of end user traffic.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <section title="Voluntary BGP Session Teardown Recommendations">
                <t>
                    Before an operator commences activities which can cause disruption to the flow of data through the lower layer network, an operator would do well to Administratively Shutdown the BGP sessions running across the lower layer network and wait a few minutes for data-plane traffic to subside.
                </t>
                <t>
                    While architectures exist to facilitate quick network reconvergence (such as <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtgwg-bgp-pic">BGP PIC</xref>), an operator cannot assume the remote side has such capabilities.
                    As such, a grace period between the Administrative Shutdown and the impacting maintenance activities is warranted.
                </t>
                <t>
                    After the maintenance activities have concluded, the operator is expected to restore the BGP sessions to their original Administrative state.
                </t>
                <section title="Maintenance Communication Considerations">
                    <t>
                        Initiators of the Administrative Shutdown are encouraged to use <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-shutdown">Shutdown Communication</xref> to inform the remote side on the nature and duration of the maintenance activities.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Involuntary BGP Session Teardown Recommendations">
                <t>
                    In the case where multilateral interconnection between BGP speakers is facilitated through a switched layer-2 fabric, such as commonly seen at Internet Exchange Points (IXPs), different operational considerations can apply.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Operational experience shows many network operators are unable to carry out the Voluntary BGP Session Teardown recommendations, because of the operational cost and risk of co-ordinating the two configuration changes required. This has an adverse affect on Internet performance.
                 </t>
                <t>
                    In the absence of notifications from the lower layer (e.g. ethernet link down) consistent with the planned maintenance activities in a densely meshed multi-node layer-2 fabric, the caretaker of the fabric could opt to cull BGP sessions on behalf of the stakeholders connected to the fabric.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Such culling of control-plane traffic will pre-empt the loss of end-user traffic, by causing the expiration of BGP Hold Timers ahead of the moment where the expiration would occur without intervention from the fabric's caretaker.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In this scenario, BGP Session Culling is accomplished through the application of a combined layer-3 and layer-4 packet filter deployed in the switched fabric itself.
                </t>
                <section title="Packet Filter Considerations">
                    <t>
                        The packet filter should be designed and specified in a way that:
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t>
                                only affect link-local BGP traffic i.e. forming part of the control plane of the system described, rather than multihop BGP which merely transits
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                only affect BGP, i.e. TCP/179
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                make provision for the bidirectional nature of BGP, i.e. that sessions may be established in either direction
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                affect all relavent AFIs
                            </t>
                        </list>
                    <xref target="acl1" /> contains an example of such a packet filter.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Monitoring Considerations">
                <t>
                    The caretaker of the lower layer can monitor dataplane traffic (e.g. interface counters) and carry out the maintenance without impact to traffic once session culling is complete.
                </t>
            </section>

        </section>


<!--
        <section anchor="Acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>
                The authors would like to thank the following people for their
                comments, support and review....
            </t>
        </section>
-->
        <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>
                There are no security considerations.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                This document has no actions for IANA.
            </t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271.xml"?>
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-idr-shutdown-07"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-ietf-rtgwg-bgp-pic-01"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5880.xml"?>
        </references>

        <section anchor="acl1" title="Example packet filter for an IPv4 subnet">
<figure>
<preamble>
    Example for an IXP with LAN prefixes 192.0.2.0/24 and 2001:db8:2::/64.
</preamble>
<artwork><![CDATA[
filter bgp_cull {
    term sourced_by_peeringlan-v4 {
        from {
            source-port 179;
            ip-source-address {
                192.0.2.0/24;
            }
        }
        then {
            count bgp_cull;
            discard;
        }
    }
    term towards_peeringlan-v4 {
        from {
            destination-port 179;
            ip-destination-address {
                192.0.2.0/24;
            }
        }
        then {
            count bgp_cull;
            discard;
        }
    }
    term sourced_by_peeringlan-v6 {
        from {
            source-port 179;
            ip-version {
                ipv6 {
                    ip6-source-address {
                        2001:db8:2::/64;
                    }
                }
            }
        }
        then {
            count bgp_cull;
            discard;
        }
    }
    term towards_peeringlan-v6 {
        from {
            destination-port 179;
            ip-version {
                ipv6 {
                    ip6-destination-address {
                        2001:db8:2::/64;
                    }
                }
            }
        }
        then {
            count bgp_cull;
            discard;
        }
    }
    term rest {
        then accept;
    }
}
]]></artwork>
<postamble>
    Junos Layer 2 Firewall example
</postamble>
</figure>
</section>

    </back>

</rfc>
